so let's talk more about the predict
not-taken predictor which is the
simplest predictor we can have it
amounts to simply incrementing the PC so
this predictor is very simple because
all it requires us is to increment the
PC we know the PC from which we fetch
the branch we know how big the
instruction is we can just increment the
PC so there is really no memory to this
predictor or anything else we have to do
the increment of the PC anyway once we
figure out it's not a branch so this
predictor pretty much uses the hardware
we have to have anyway but the question
is how accurate is it a rule of thumb is
that about 20% of all instructions are
branches so 80% of the time this
predictor will be correct because it's
simply not a branch instruction for
branches a little more over half of the
branches are taken so let's say that 60%
of branches are taken so what we get is
that this predictor is correct 80% of
the time for non branches and also
another 8% of all the instructions
because of the 40% of branches that are
not taken it is incorrect 12% of the
time it is incorrect 60 percent of 20
percent which amounts to 12% now if we
know the misprediction penalty we can
easily compute what is the impact on CPI
of branch mispredictions the CPI will be
1 plus 12% times the penalty in a 5
stage pipeline this would be 2 so the
CPI would be one point 24